Guide to the Edward Otho Cresap Ord Letters, 1854-1885
Department of Special Collections
- Correspondence, 1859 -1863 Dec. 7 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 48. 1863, July 17.Jacson, Miss. To [Molly]. NP.
    "lively siege and pretty sharp investment... enemy have retreated," town gutted, "I have not heard wether [sic] the President has approved Gen'l. Grant's summary process of ejecting McClernand & putting me in his place," corps, waste of life, desolation, seizing supplies, relieved Gen. Lanman.
  - 49. 1863, July 25.NP. To Bertie. NP.
    Advice, personal.
  - 50. [1863], Aug. 6.NP. AL.
    "slaughtering men to no purpose and I feel ashamed". Fragment.
  - 51. 1863, Sept. 7.Memphis, Tenn. "On board Steamer Welcome, Miss. River". To [Molly]. NP.
    Childrens' schooling drawing and perspective, sketches of RR etc., teaching French, on way to New Orleans, "I wonder if parents like Judge Ord don't sometimes neglect children who are deformed."
  - 52. 1863, Sept. 17.New Orleans, HQ 13th Army Corps. To [Molly]. NP.
    Preparing for field, trip, considerable sickness here, Mr. Cresap, Col. Sinclair, [Molly's] opinions based on the word of those around her and not on careful study.
  - 53. 1863, Sept. 25.New Orleans, HQ 13th Army Corps. To [Molly]. NP.
    Mr. Cresap, "The citizens not much in love with Gen'l. Butlers rule... Gen'l. Banks & Stone... are trying to efface by amiability the bad impression left by Gen'l. Butler," carpet and memories.
  - 54. 1863, Dec. 7.Guard House, Philadelphia. To Molly. NP.
    Trip, Philadelphia, on sick leave, personal with Dec. 3 receipt for grave of Lilly Ord.
- Correspondence, 1863 Dec. 12 -1866 Sept. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1. [1863], Dec. 12-13.New York. To [Molly]. NP.
    Patent and invention, lost box, poor health, Dr. Forbes, children's concert, Peacock dead, Col. Dinnick., to leave for New Orleans, "I don't expect much politeness or attention from Stanton" "may not have to go to Texas."
  - 2. 1864, Jan. 8.In the Field, Va. HQ Dept. of Va. & N.Carolina, Army of the James. To [Molly]. NP.
    Butler relieved, Ord temporarily in command, Wilmington affair, get family quarters at Old Point, Grant will ask that Ord retain command, Ord not really pleased, Butler has been polite and considerate, Gen. Lockwood.
  - 3. 1864, Jan. 10.In the Field, -Va. To [Molly]. NP.
    "Gen'l. Butler is a shrewd and influential politician and hence he may return to the command of the Dept.," "received a [putty] -silk flag captured at Fort Harrison by my corps the day I was wounded ... I propose sending it to the California Senate ... flag of the 27th Va. Artillery." Richmond, deserters.
  - 4. 1864, Jan. 13."On board Steamer in the James River." To [Molly]. NP.
    Butler to turn over command to Ord at Old Point, old Mr. Blair is in Richmond as a peace maker.
  - 5. 1864, Feb. 8.[Ducious?] Point Pass, Cavalle., Texas. To [Molly]. NP.
    Trip, inspected corps, Indianola, to visit Aransas & Pt. Isabel.
  - 6. 1864, Mar. 24.Louisville, Ky. To Capt. H.G. Brown.
    Special Orders, to report to Ord at Washington by telegraph, Mar. 25. Cincinnati, Ohio. To Molly. [Louisville?]. To stay at Miss Manning's in Washington, box arrived.
  - 7. 1864, Mar. 30.Washington D.C. To [Molly]. NP.
    "Saw Gen'l. G...he will give me a command," trip delayed at Pittsburg.
  - 8. 1864, April 3.Ebbitt House Washington, D.C. To [Molly]. Louisville, Ky.
    Memories, Gen. Averell and reception "my cough was relieved directly by a day in Cumberland the air of those regions is not tainted," joke from Gen'l. Crook, colored girl -Ord's black cousin, Gov. Yates, "I would like to go a little into politics but it is not a very honorable or truthful profession just now," Banks anecdote.
  - 9. 1864, April 9.Cumberland, Md. To Molly. NP.
    "have not had a very delightful time with Sigel," "Gen'l. Grant did intend a Department for me ... politicians and elections interfered ... I feel that in changing Banks for Sigel I have gained a loss."
  - 10. 1864, April 11.Cumberland, Md. To (Molly). NP.
    Personal., some interference with letters, politics and Army.
  - 11. 1864, April 15.Cumberland, Md. To [Molly]. Louisville, Ky.
    "I fear someone to whom my letters are not directed must get hold of them," health advice, Sigel.
  - 12. 1864, April 16.Cumberland, Md. To [Molly]. NP.
    Sent official report of affair at Iuka which gave Rosencrans [sic] his glory, Ords part, kept back by Grant, invention, politics and command, Ringgold dead, California earthquake, duties under political generals not pleasant.
  - 13. 1864, April 20-21.Cumberland. To Molly. NP.
    Joke about black cousin, relieved of duty, Sigel jealous, Banks Army has had a reverse which he tries to palm off on the 13th Corps and Gen'l. Stoneman, book about Cresap family, experiments.
  - 14. 1864, April 23.Baltimore, Md. To [Molly]. [Louisville].
    Experiments, Henry (exslave) Ord relieved at own request, joke about Mary Keyes.
  - 15. 1864, July 4.Maltby House, Baltimore, Md. To [Molly]. NP.
    Patent business, European baths, Sherman in Marietta, rebel raid on B & 0 RR, draft bill, Sigel's defeat.
  - 16. 1864, July 6.Baltimore, To [Molly]. NP.
    Washington raid or near and confusion, personal.
  - 17. 1864, July 8."Gen'l. Grant's HQ." To [Molly]. NP.
    Offered a command against Early at & near Harpers Ferry, visit lines in front of Petersburg.
  - 18. 1864, July 9-14.City Point, Va. To [Molly]. NP.
    Gillmore to command troops assembling on Potomac, Gen. Meade... "courteous, pleasant gentleman." Col. Morgan, Col. Gobson, [loss of children seems very common]. French officers visit lines and trenches, July 14, Baltimore ordered to Washington.
  - 19. 1864, July 17.Baltimore, Md. To (Molly]. [Bel Air].
    Rebel raid at Baltimore and Washington, to see Grant, Gen. Wright, "the politicians still control matters here -or seek to control them so that a general who is simply governed by military interests and discards politics would be pulled to pieces and turned away," railroad not working, Bel Air, "will probably be assigned to a command in front of Petersburg," Molly wants to move east.
  - 20. 1864, July 19.City Point, Va. To [Molly]. [Bel Air].
    Personal, command of 10th Corps, "if you remain in the city (Baltimore) among the secessionists -you can do me a deal of harm."
  - 21. 1864, July 20-21.City Point, Va. To[Molly]. [Bel Air].
    Re: moving, expected child, "Gen'l. Grant and the Sectys. of War and State have been very kind and complimentary," important command, President's call for half a million men, notes to children, has not been in battle at Monocacy.
  - 22. [1864,] July 21.City Point, Va. To [Molly]. [Bel Air].
    Command of 18th Corps, works in front of Petersburg, the rebel raid at Baltimore and Washington, Gen. Franklin's escape, newspaper reports of Andersonville, Georgia "60 or 70 die a day -and they in their misery are murdering each other," "try and get with people who do not hate the government I serve -who do not conspire to have me murdered for there are plenty in Baltimore who do this, and would be delighted could they get me shot or consigned to a rebel dungeon."
  - 23. [1864], July 25.Ebbitt House, Washington, D.C. To [Molly]. [Bel Air].
    Has been in New York, visited Sen.Nesmith, Gen. Grant, Sec. of State, to see President next day, Grant's appointment confirmed, cholera in N.Y.
  - 24. 1864, July 26.Near Petersburg, Va. To [Molly]. NP.
    Personal, command, "have some black troops with me", reasons he was relieved of command at Baltimore.
  - 25. 1864, July 28.HQ 18th Corps. To [Molly]. [Bel Air].
    Personal, Martinsburg raid, on temperance list for 6 months, peace effort and Grant.
  - 26. 1864, July 29.Camp Near Petersburg, Va. To [Molly]. [Bel Air].
    Road to Baltimore dangerous, personal, not satisfied with situation.
  - 27. [1864, July 31].Near Petersburg, Va. To Molly. [Bel Air].
    Personal, "what a sad sad thing is war --we had it here in all its horrors yesterday...thousands, were killed and wounded to no apparent and or purpose ... I feel quite sick with shame at being unable to even say what I think, or help to stop it," "I do want to quit this murderous business."
  - 28. [1864], July 31.NP. To Berty. NP. Personal.
  - 29. 1864, Aug. 2 & 3.Near Petersburg. To [Molly]. [Bel Air].
    "our troops having encountered a repulse ... unnecessarily men have been overtasked, Genls. Butler & Meade, Gen'l. Burnsides burst up, advice re: children.
  - 30. 1864, Aug. 5.Petersburg. To Molly. [Bel Air].
    Waiting for "public matters" to be settled," box, Molly's confinement, official visitors, fiasco, Burnside.
  - 31. 1864, Aug. 8.Near Petersburg. To Molly. [Bel Air].
    "Burnside had the management of the whole affair --arranging and posting and ordering forward all the troops of his and my corps -until Gen'l. Meade discovered he was involving his men in great unnecessary confusion and loss when he ordered the assault to cease...but Burnside do not have sense enough to know ... the enemy were surrounding [him] and kept them [his men] inside the enemies works in a big deep hole where they could do nothing and where they were slaughtered," country fevers, personal, sutlers elected by Regts. and requires capital.
  - 32. 1864, Aug. 10.Near Petersburg, Va. To [Molly]. [Bel Air].
    "the President has confirmed me in command of the 18th Corps," wanted 13th, investigation of Burnsides fiasco, Richmond papers -"their statements of military affairs are rather what they wish than what happens --the newspapers on both sides are more controlled by interests than truth," explosion of a boat of ordnance stores at City Point, 40 killed, mines and trench war.
  - 33. 1864, Aug. 11-12.HQ 18th Army Corps. To [Molly]. [Bel Air].
    "feeling of utter indifference to success...enthusiasm...all gone -on both sides," "men are worn out," trench warfare, lack of officers, note to children.
  - 34. 1864, Aug. 14.Near Petersburg. To [Molly]. [Bel Air].
    Has malaria, trench warfare, "much less bitter feeling displayed by both sides as they both become more exhausted," prospects of peace, enemy deserters, [Berkely] deserted, rain.
  - 35. 1864, Aug. 17.Near Petersburg, Va. To [Molly]. [Bel Air].
    Armistice and peace propositions, wants to go to Washington "give them some insight into the causes of the state of affairs here," new staff officer son of Secy. of Navy Welles, trench warfare, field hospital.
  - 36. 1864, Aug. 19.Near Petersourg. To [Molly]. [Bel Air].
    Personal, food, pay accounts far behind, trench warfare.
  - 37. 1864, Aug. 24.Near Petersburg. To [Molly]. [Bel Air].
    A Rebel success and loss (5 Rebel Generals), heavy losses in trench warfare, moving back for awhile "I wish the government and country were one" who can make peace, one child a little deaf, suggestion to recruit in California.
  - 38. 1864, Aug. 26.Near Bermuda hundred. To [Molly]. [Bel Air].
    A quieter camp, Butler is Ord's C.O., thinks B. may run for President, Hancock's fight with Lee, deserters, peace hopes, memory or dream of Lilly.
  - 39. 1864, Aug. 29.In the Field, Va. HQ 18th Army Corps. To [Molly]. [Bel Air].
    Hunter and Strother, "there are tyranies worse than President Lincolns ... I say all this with no high admiration of the latter -and but little respect for the military ability his administration displays," peace hopes and problems, war badly managed.
  - 40. [1864], Aug. 30.Bermuda Hundred, Petersburg., Va. To [Molly]. [Bel Air].
    Inquiry into Burnside disaster, testimony personal. Fragment.
  - 41. 1864, Sept. 4.In the Field, Va. HQ 18th Army Corps. To [Molly]. [Bel Air]
    Going on leave, to look for a house in Norfolk and stop in Washington, Gen'l. Gibbon, sickness, Sherman, evacuation of Atlanta, no money,
  - 42. 1864, Sept. 21.HQ 18th Army Corps, Army of the James. To [Molly]. [Bel Air].
    In Washington saw Sec. of War and Gen. Halleck, Sheridan's success, expenses.
  - 43. 1864, Nov. 28.Old Point, Va. To [Molly]. NP.
    Trip across bay, housing, land $50 an acre, to go with Butler to the front, appointment rumors.
  - 44. 1864, Nov. 30.Near Richmond. To [Molly]. NP.
    Portsmouth, Gen. Vogdes, the Butlers, baby.
  - 45. 1864, Dec. 1.HQ 18th Army Corps, Army of the James. To [Molly]. NP.
    Personal business, petroleum.
  - 46. 1864, Dec. 3.Near Richmond. To [Molly]. NP.
    Personal, command increased.
  - 47. 1864, Dec. 5.Near Richmond. To [Molly]. NP.
    New quarters, government restriction on paying officers' accounts.
  - 48. 1864, Dec. 8.Fort Monroe, Va. To [Molly]. NP.
    Poor health, command increased, President's message, Secy. Seward, hopes for promotion.
  - 49. 1864, Dec. 11.In the Field, Va. To [Molly]. NP.
    Grant's permission to go on sick leave, Butler will not be Secy. of War, family illnesses, Mrs. Grant.
  - 50. 1864, Dec. 13.In the Field, Va. To [Molly]. NP [Baltimore].
    Brother going on leave, short of funds, waiting for Butler, health and medication, Mrs. Grant and other ladies visit front where Ord took a Fort and was wounded, scarlet fever.
  - 51. 1864, Dec. 14.In the Field, Va. To [Molly]. [Baltimore].
    Letters arrive open "by mistake," bills, commands 25-30 thousand, rank in regulars, Meade and high-ranking staff, visit of Lord [Newey].
  - 52. [1864, Dec.].In the Field, Va. To [Molly]. [Baltimore].
    [South] considering arming and freeing negroes "everything signifies the failure of their rebellion," Lee and wife, "a mans wife has an instinct which is often times better than his judgement", "I am writing to Mr. Seward -as one of the leaders of policy which may turn the tide... I wonder sometimes if Mr. Lincoln and Mr. Seward and others feel their responsibilities -I fear they do not," note to Berty re: Christmas and Chris Ringle. Fragment: begins on page 5.
  - 53. 1864, Dec. 23.In the Field. To [Molly]. [Baltimore].
    Host of French naval officer and consul, Butler not back, news from deserters that "Savannah is ours -also Fort Fisher," "I have shrewd suspicions that the rebs have some understanding with that arch leader Boney -by which when the worst comes to the worst -they will get France and England to help them...," Sherman's march through Georgia, Pvt. McCullough.
  - 54. [1865?], Jan. 6.Old Point., Va. To [Molly]. [Baltimore].
    Working on gun model, "a little mad at Gen'l. Weitzel being ahead of me in obtaining the quarters here," to return with Butler and Grant, mail, family to come down.
  - 55. 1865, Mar. 31.Humphreys, Station, Va. To [Molly]. [Old Point].
    Advanced line a mile and a half "and my troops have taken about 2 hundred prisoners," Gen'ls. Gibbon, Turner, Foster and Birney and Gen'l. Harris, saw Sherman, Sheridan and Creek at City Point comments on first 2, "I am not as sanguine as Gen'l. Gibbon who thinks we ought to finish the war this time," has Dept., on scout.
  - 56. 1865, April 3."Behind Richmond". To Molly. NP.
    "We are after Lee and his Army who left Richmond yesterday & Petersburg last night," Gen'ls. Hill & Wise killed, fought successfully at Petersburg "the military consistency of Lee's Army is apparently all gone," Gen. [Hech] had to swim Appomatox to escape Union cavalry.
  - 57. 1866, May 31-June 4.Marquette - Superior City. To [Molly]. NP.
    Run over lake, Sherman "not here yet" deserted Superior City.
  - 58. 1866, Aug. 24.Cairo, Ill. To Molly. NP.
    Trip from St. Louis, cholera, Hooker took Ord's old command, confidential papers contains an old letter on the Fenians.
  - 59. 1866, Aug. 30.Little Rock, Ark. To [Molly]. NP.
    Trip, arrival, Duvalls Bluff, cholera, description Little Rock, Molly "confined," Sherman's eldest son died of fever at Vicksburg, meals, "People here are not very well pleased with the state of affairs," note to Berty.
  - 60. 1866, Sept. 9.HQ Ft. Gibson Cherokee Nation. To [Molly]. NP. [Detroit?].
    Trip, Indian Commissioners, Mrs. Barbour, town of Van Buren, arrival at Ft. Smith, surgers of African church, President's visit, Radical convention -Chandler & Wade, personal. Fragment: pp. 3 & 4 missing.
  - 61. 1866, Sept. 14.Little Rock, Ark. To [Molly]. [Detroit] AL.
    Birth of Jules Slaughter Ord, sickness. Fragment.
  - 62. 1866, Sept. 18.Little Rock, Ark. To Mollie. [Detroit]
    Cholera wards, will make HQ at Ft. Smith "where Gen'l. Taylor had his before he was President," war damage, Richmond paper gives Ord credit for last success over Lee, personal, Col. Brown.
  - 63. [1866, Sept. ?].Little Rock, Ark. To [Mollie]. [Detroit].
    Another inspection tour, local visitors, coming home in Oct., "the southern sentiment among the common people in the woods is vindictive." Fragment: first two pages missing.
  - 64. 1866, Sept. 22.Little Rock to [Mollie]. NP.
    Looking for HQ up-river, Fayetteville, going into Indian territory, conservatives and radicals
- Correspondence, 1866 Oct. -1879 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1. 1866, Oct. 1-2.Fort Smith. To [Molly]. [Detroit].
    Fayetteville, boarding house, Mrs. Quarles, meals, Van Buren, "houses ... have been burned or gone to reck in the war which in point of ferocity was no where more terrible than here," to go to Ft. Gibson, orders from Sherman.
  - 2. 1866, Oct. 4.Ft. Gibson, Cherokee Nation. To Molly. [Detroit].
    To go to Ft. Arbuckle, travel, reflections, Hooker, Mrs. Gilman.
  - 2a. 1867, July 30.Vicksburg, Miss. To Gen. U.S. Grant at Washington.
  - 3. [1868-71?].HQ Dept. of Calif., San Francisco. To Gen'l. [Sherman?]. NP.
    Calif. and Nevada politicians, Crook, Apache War -contractors interest in continuing it, Visalia, Sierras, losses of soldier wagon-masters, bloody canon, Yosemite -Nevada and Vernal falls. Fragment: possibly two -pp. 1-4 or 14-[10 or 17].
  - 4. 1870, Mar. 28.Ft. Wingate, New Mexico. To [Molly]. NP.
    Snow in Sierra Blancas, short of rations, on way to Camp Whipple, Arizona and Prescott, greenbacks rising, bill before Congress to dispense with two Brig. Gen'ls.
  - 5. 1871, Dec. 11.Omaha, Nebraska. To [Molly]. NP.
    Trip Dept., Gen'l. Alvord, descr. of area, food and game incl. buffalo.
  - 6. [1871?].NP. To [Molly]. NP.
    House, carpets, prices,warm in sum[mer]. Nappa [sic]. Frag.
  - 7. [1871?].NP To [Molly]. NP.
    Packing and moving, Maj. Lord, heading toward S.F. Frag. or PS.
  - 8. [1872, Jan.][Omaha?]. To Molly & Lucy. NP.
    Snow, sledding, looking for house, Col. Preston, greenbacks, frag?
  - 9. [1872, Feb.?].[Omaha]. Bertie to Papa. NP.
    Family scene, note: "By memory and not accurate" R.M.O. dated 1873 prob. wrong.
  - 10. 1872, Mar. 19.Omaha, Neb. To [Molly]. NP. AL.
    Personal, poetic valentine from Bertie, tour. Fragment.
  - 11. 1877, June 20.Fort Clark, [Tex.]. To Lucy. NP.
    Girls secrets, letter to Mrs. Shafter, warns against Mr. Morganthau, Piedras Negras and Mexican Garrison, Gen. Trevino, welcome, ladies and revolution, Ft. Duncan, stone buildings of Ft. Clark, Col. & Mrs. Shafter, Escobedo, Lerdo & Diaz.
  - 12. 1877, Dec. 24.San Antonio. To Lucy. NP.
    Trip, Gen'l. Mason, rains, family news.
  - 13. [1877-79?].NP. To [Lucy?]. NP.
    Family, Garesche, Bertie. Frag.
  - 14. [1877-79?].NP. To [Lucy]. NP.
    To visit Stockton and Davis with Jim. Frag.
  - 15. [1877-79?].[San Antonio]. To [Lucy]. NP.
    Tutor for Garesche, Bertie's beaux, gossip. Frag.
  - 16. 1878. Feb. 14.Fort Duncan. To Lucy. NP.
    Inspection tour, school, family news and gossip, Shafters.
  - 17. 1878, Feb. 17.San Antonio. Molly Ord to Lucy. NP.
    Valentines "cobra morgus" encloses valentine.
  - 18. 1878, April 11.San Antonio, Tex. To Lucy. NP.
    Family news, Maj. Emory's death, Masons, prices.
  - 19. 1878, April 23.San Antonio. To Lucy. NP.
    Kitty's wedding, presents, etc., Indians pretty lively on Rio Grande.
  - 20. 1878, July 12.Washington, D.C. To Lucy. NP.
    Advice to daughters, poverty, Gen. Macfeely.
  - 21. 1878, July 31.San Antonio, Tex. To Lucy and Bertie. NP.
    Personal, sickness, family.
  - 22. 1878, Aug. 1.San Antonio. M.M. Ord & E.O.C. Ord to Bertie. NP.
    Darragh divorce, news (difficult to read), yellow fever quarantines, Fitz John Porter case.
  - 23. 1878, Aug. 15.San Antonio. To Lucy. NP.
    Water stimulation, dog & Garresch, personal, social manners?, new servant with amputated hand.
  - 24. 1878, Aug. 15.San Antonio. Mollie (daughter) and E.O.C. to Bertie [Rawley].
    Family news, advice.
  - 25. 1878, Aug. 24.San Antonio. To Lucy. NP.
    Local and family news, Col. Brown, "Congress has passed a law which stops the promotion of all Lieuts."
  - 26. 1878, Aug. 30.San Antonio. To Lucy. NP.
    Advice, Van Vliets, family news.
  - 27. 1878 Sept. 17.San Antonio. To Lucy & Bertie [Washington, D.C.].
    Family news, Garesche's whipping, schools, "Conscript" by Erkmann Chartrain, "call on Mrs. Crary the wife of Secty. of War," Miss Sallie's move from Georgetown.
  - 28. 1878, Dec. 28.San Antonio. To Lucy. [Washington, D.C.].
    Christmas, Gen. Trevino, Galveston, family news, Miss Sherman, "find out the wife or daughters if there are any of Mr. Atkins (J.D.C.) M.C. -from Tennessee -and do all the polite to them you can -he is chairman of the appropriation committee in the house and is a nice gentleman. You will soon learn if you stay in Washington long enough that the wives of the M.C.s and members of cabinets have almost as much patronage as their husbands and I want you to make the acquaintance mainly of the nice southern people they are much less mercenary and I think more honest than the northern politicians."
  - 29. 1879, Jan. 8.[San Antonio]. To Lucy. [Washington, D.C.].
    Mexican officers, Gen. Trevino, Col. Andrews at Galveston, Genls. Cord & Vincent, Mr. Limpky, locked out, Grant & Taylor, advice.
  - 30. 1879, Jan. 16.San Antonio. To Lucy. [Washington, D.C.].
    Vaccinations, schooling.
  - 31. 1879, Jan. 24-28.San Antonio. To Lucy. [Washington, D.C.]. A.L.
    Mr. Schleicher's burial, Mr. Rainy, "somewhat surprised at the shabby looking Jacals in which Mexican families live," family news, hopes to go to Washington, theatre burned, new bridges and buildings, spring, riding, horses.
  - 32. [1879], Aug. 18.San Antonio. Ruth and E.O.C. to "Mama." NP.
    Birthdays, boils, dental work, John & Lucy still live on the island, Bertie and the "litterary," court martial.
  - 33. 1879, Aug. 19.San Antonio. To [Molly (wife)]. NP.
    A funeral of young girl who died of Brights disease, family, Lucy & Johnny on island, Senator Conkling's scrap with Mrs. Sprague -"sad comments the absurdity of building for happiness upon a wealthy match," gossip.
  - 34. 1879, Aug. 20.San Antonio. E.O.C. & Bertie to [Molly] (wife). NP.
    Boil, Col. Blunt and Gilmore, court martial ended, Patterson funeral, Fragment, torn.
  - 35. 1879, Aug. 21.San Antonio. To [Molly] (wife). NP.
    Dyspepsia, memories of Camp Verde and camels, boys' exam, children, Jimmie's reputation, boil (6pp.).
  - 36. 1879, Aug. 27.San Antonio. To Wife. Walnut Grove.
    Children, Gen. & Mrs. Sweitzer, Gen. Vincent, Lt. Howard, Col. Peurose, family news.
  - 37. 1879, Aug. 31.Fort Ringgold, Texas. Gen. F. Mason to [Lucy Ord Mason]. San Antonio. ALS.
    Journey, roads to Ft. Brown & San Diego.
  - 38. [1879, Aug./Sept.?].NP. To [Molly]. NP. ALS.
    Exams, Army vacancies, children. Frag. pp. 5 & 6 only.
  - 39. [1879, Aug. -Oct.?].NP. To Molly.
    Postcript, M's letter of 24th, exams, vacancies. Frag. pp. 5 & 6 only.
  - 40. [1879, Aug. -Oct.?].NP. To [Molly]. NP. AL.
    Wants increased pay for Bvt. Maj. Genls. who have equal duties, Angur, children's education, RR passes. Frag. 2 unnumbered pages.
  - 41. [1879, Aug. -Oct.?].[San Antonio]. To [Molly]. NP.
    Children, clothing, when Ned & Johnny get assigned. Frag, corner only.
  - 42. 1879, Sept. 1.San Antonio. To Wife. NP.
    Children, local news, Mrs. Freidlander, dental work, new law closing saloons, Lt. Rousseau in jail.
  - 43. 1879, Sept. 9.San Antonio. To Wife. NP.